Finding Aid for Historica Critica sound recordings and videotapes, 1984-1992
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Historica Critica sound recordings and videotapes 1984-1992
Historica Critica.
2 linear feet
90139 Bimu M3 2
University of Michigan faculty group interested in the history of the university. Sound recordings and videotapes of interviews with former University of Michigan faculty, regents, administrators, and other interested individuals about the history of the university.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Materials donated in a series of accessions, 1988-1992, by Historica Critica (Donor No. 7607 ).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open to research, except where otherwise noted. Individual interview may be closed at the specification of the interviewee of for lack of a release from the interviewee.
Historica Critica is a group of active and retired University of Michigan faculty and alumni who believe that the history of the university should be more fully studied, recorded, and celebrated. Toward these ends, Historica Critica has compiled video- and audiotapes of interviews with significant figures of the university faculty, administration, and alumni. The ultimate goal of Historica Critica is to bring about a comprehensive and scholarly history of the university through the use of these tapes.
Members of Historica Critica who have worked on the interview project include: Claude Eggertsen, School of Education; Allen Britton, School of Music Dean; Robert Iglehart, School of Art; Ralph Loomis, English Humanities; Allan Jones, Prakken Publications; Warner Rice, English; Arnold Kuethe, Aerospace Engineering; Arthur Gallagher, former editor of the Ann Arbor News.
Historica Critica has its own criteria for judging whether a member of the university community merits inclusion in its field of significant figures. These criteria, while undefined, seem to cast a net which primarily includes high-level university administrators, Regents, and emeritus faculty. Presidents Fleming and Hatcher; Vice-Presidents Smith, Niehuss, and Pierpont; Regents Roach and Power; and Emeritus faculty Ackley, William Bishop, Britton, Dow, Kuethe, Maurer, Rucknagel, Sears, and Wegman are among those interviewed. Men prominent on the local Ann Arbor scene are also included: Arthur Gallagher, editor of the Ann Arbor News; George Sallade, Ann Arbor Democrat; and Albert Wheeler, former mayor of Ann Arbor.
The materials in the Historica Critica collection are arranged first according to the medium on which the interview is preserved: Reel-to-Reel Audiotapes, Cassette Audiotapes, and Videotapes. Within each medium, the materials are in alphabetical order according to the subject of the interview. Some of the reel-to-reel audiotapes have more than one interview subject; these are arranged alphabetically according to the primary subject. It appears that the interviewers transferred the materials on reel-to-reel audiotapes directly to cassettes in several cases. This facilitates the arrangement of the cassettes into alphabetical order according to subject. The dates listed in the finding aid are the dates of the interview. Summaries of the interviews, prepared by Virginia Harris, are found in Box 1.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--History--20th century.
Contributors:
Ackley, Gardner.; Bishop, Ronald.; Bishop, William W. (William Warner), 1906-1987; Britton, Allen Perdue.; Dow, William G. (William Gould), 1895-1999; Eggertsen, Claude A. (Claude Andrew), 1909-; Fleming, R. W. (Robben Wright), 1916-2010.; Gallagher, Arthur, 1911-; Halstead, Claribel Baird, 1904-; Hatcher, Harlan, 1898-1998.; Iglehart, Robert Leslie, 1912-; Kaplan, Wilfred, 1915-; Kuethe, Arnold M. (Arnold Martin), 1905-; Lehmann, Charles Frederick, 1922-; Lesch, James.; Maurer, Wesley Henry, 1897-; Niehuss, Marvin Lemmon, 1903-2003; Ocker, Phyllis.; Pierpont, Wilbur K., 1914-; Power, Eugene B., 1905-; Rucknagel, Donald L.; Sallade, George Wahr, 1922-; Sawyer, Charles Henry, 1906-; Sears, John.; Smith, Allan Frederick, 1911-; Wegman, Myron E., 1908-; Wheeler, Albert Harold, 1915-1994.; Roach, Thomas A., 1929-; Marshall, Norma E.; Storey, Alfred W.; Super, R. H. (Robert Henry), 1914-1996.
Genre Terms:
Oral histories.; Videotapes.
- Papers
  - Summaries of interviews, 1 folders (Box 1)
- Audiotapes 1985-1987
  - Reel-to-Reel
    - William W. Bishop, Jr. (Professor of International Law) and Eugene Power (Regent) February 10, 1987 (Box 1)
    - William Dow (Professor of Electrical Engineering) May 13, 1986, 2 reels (Box 1)
    - Arthur Gallagher (Editor, Ann Arbor News) February 20, 1987, 2 reels (Box 1)
    - Arnold Kuethe, (Professor of Aerospace Engineering) March 10, 1985, 2 reels (Box 1)
    - Wesley Maurer (Professor of Journalism) April 19, 1985 (2 reels) (Box 1)
    - Marvin Niehuss (Vice-President and Secretary), Harlan Hatcher (President), and Donald Rucknagel (Professor of Human Genetics) May 27, 1986, February 20, 1987, 3 reels (Box 1)
    - Wilbur Pierpont (Vice-President Finance) undated (Box 1)
    - George Sallade (Alumnus, Ann Arbor Democrat) May 20, 1986, 2 reels (Box 1)
    - Allan Smith (Interim President) October 29, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Myron Wegman (Professor of Public Health) and John Sears (Professor in Medical School) June 10, 1986, 3 reels (Box 1)
  - Cassette Tapes 1986-1989
    - Gardner Ackley, (Professor of Economics) June 16, 1987 (2 cassettes) (Box 1)
    - William W. Bishop, Jr., (Professor of International Law) February 10, 1987, 2 audiocassettes (Box 1)
    - Allen Britton (Dean, School of Music) and Thomas Roach (Regent), Fall? 1987 (Box 1)
    - William Dow (Professor of Electrical Engineering) May 13, 1986, 2 audiocassettes (Box 1)
    - Arthur Gallagher (Editor Ann Arbor News), February 24, 1987, 2 audiocassettes (Box 1)
    - Claribel Baird Halstead (Professor of Speech) March 28, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Harlan Hatcher (President) April 28, 1987, 2 audiocassettes (Box 1)
    - Arnold Kuethe (Professor of Aerospace Engineering) March 10, 1987, 2 audiocassettes (Box 1)
    - James Lesch (Director, DRDA) September 22, 1987, 2 audiocassettes (Box 1)
      [Access restricted pending receipt of release]
    - Norma Marshal (Nursing School, associate dean) February 17, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Marvin Niehuss (Vice-President and Secretary) May 26, 1986, 2 audiocassettes (Box 1)
    - Wilbur Pierpont (Vice-President Finance) undated (Box 1)
    - Eugene Power (Regent) November 11, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Donald Rucknagel (Professor of Human Genetics) February 20, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Allan Smith (Interim President) October 29, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Myron Wegman (Professor of Public Health) and John Sears (Professor at Medical School) June 10, 1986, 3 audiocassettes (Box 1)
    - Albert Wheeler (Mayor of Ann Arbor, Professor of Microbiology) September 29, 1987, 2 audiocassettes (Box 1)
- Videotapes
  The Videotapes series consists of videocassettes of interviews with Allan P. Britton, Robert H. Super, Claude Eggertsen, Wilfred Kaplan, Charles H. Sawyer, Phyllis M. Ocker, Robert Iglehart, Ronald C. Bishop, Charles Lehmann, Alfred Storey, and Robben W. Fleming concerning their activities at the University of Michigan.
  - 1989
    - Ronald C. Bishop (Professor of Internal Medicine) February 21, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Allen P. Britton (Dean, School of Music) December 12, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Robert Iglehart (Professor of Art) December 19, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Robben Fleming (President) October 2, 1989, 2 tapes (Box 2)
  - 1990
    - Claude A. Eggertsen, October1990, 2 tapes (Box 2)
    - Charles F. Lehmann February 1990 (Box 2)
    - Phyllis M. Ocker October 1990 (Box 2)
    - Charles H. Sawyer October 1990 (Box 2)
    - Alfred W. Storey April 1990 (Box 2)
  - 1991-1992
    - Wilfred Kaplan March 1991 (Box 2)
    - Robert H. Super April 1992 (Box 2)